<sect2>
<title>Configuring <application>NCPFS</application></title>

<sect3><title>Config files</title>
<para><filename>~/.nwclient</filename></para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Configuration Information</title>

<para>A config file <filename>~/.nwclient</filename> should be placed
in the home directory of each user that intends to use <application>ncpfs</application>. The permissions on this file should be set to 600, for obvious 
security reasons.  The configuration file should contain a single line
per server that the user will use.  Each line should contain
the server name, the user name, and optionally the password.  Below is a
sample <filename>.nwclient</filename> file.</para>

<screen><userinput># Begin example <filename>~/.nwclient</filename> config file

Server1/User1 Password
Server2/User1 
Server2/Guest1 -

# End example .nwclient config file</userinput></screen>

<para>The syntax for the <filename>.nwclient</filename> file is simple,
<userinput>server_name/user_name password</userinput>.  Be extremely
careful when creating or editing this file as the client utilities are
very picky about syntax.  There should always be a space immediately
after the username.  If this space is substituted by a tab or multiple 
spaces, you will not get the expected results when attempting to use 
the <application>NCPFS</application> tools.  If no password is supplied, 
the client utilities will ask for a password when it is needed.  If no 
password is needed, for instance when using a guest account, a single '-' 
should be put in place of a password.</para>

<para>It should be noted that the ncpmount is not intended to mount
individual volumes because each mount point creates a separate client
connection to the Novell server.  Mounting each individual volume
separately would be unwise, as mounting all volumes on a server 
under one mount point uses only one client connection.</para>

<para>If you need to set up the <acronym>IPX</acronym> protocol at boot, 
you can install the
<filename>/etc/sysconfig/network-devices/services/ipx</filename> 
network service script included with the 
<xref linkend="intro-important-bootscripts"/> package.</para>

<screen><userinput><command>make install-service-ipx</command></userinput></screen>

<para>Next install the configurations script,
<filename>ifconfig.ipx0</filename>.  The configuration assumes 
<acronym>IPX</acronym> will be set up on 
<emphasis role="strong">eth0</emphasis>  
and the network frame type is 802.2.  You should confirm that these are 
the correct settings and adjust as necessary.</para>

<para><emphasis>Note</emphasis>: This will overwrite any existing file.</para>

<screen><userinput><command>cat &gt; /etc/sysconfig/network-devices/ifconfig.ipx0 &lt;&lt; "EOF"</command>
ONBOOT=yes
SERVICE=ipx
IPXDEV=eth0
FRAME=802.2
<command>EOF</command></userinput></screen>

</sect3>

</sect2>
