<sect2>
<title>Configuring nfs-utils</title>

<sect3><title>Config files</title>
<para><filename>~/.nwclient</filename></para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Configuration Information</title>

<para>A config file <filename>~/.nwclient</filename> should be placed
in each user's home directory that intends to use ncpfs.
The permissions on this file should be set to 600, for obvious security
reasons.  The configuration file should contain a sinlge line
per server that the user will use.  Each line should contain
the sever name, the user name, and optionally the password.  Below is a
sample <filename>.nwclient</filename> file.</para>

<para><screen># Begin example <filename>~/.nwclient</filename> config file

Server1/User1 Password
Server2/User1 
Server2/Guest1 -

# End example .nwclient config file</screen></para>

<para>The syntax for the <filename>.nwclient</filename> file is simple,
<userinput>server_name/user_name password</userinput>.  Be extremely
careful when creating or editing this file as the client utilities are
very picky about syntax.  There should always be a space immediately
after the username.  If this space is substituted by a tab or multiple 
spaces, you will not get the expected results when attempting to use 
the ncpfs tools.  If no password is supplied, the client utilities will 
ask for a password when it is needed.  If no password is needed, for 
instance when using a guest account, a single '-' should be put in 
place of a password.</para>

<para>It should be noted that the ncpmount is not intended to mount
individual volumes because each mountpoint creates a separate client
connection to the Novell server.  Mounting each individual volume
separately would be unwise, as mounting all volumes on a server 
under one mount point, uses only one client connection.</para>

<para>If you need to set up the IPX protocol at boot, you can create the 
following scripts.  These scripts assume IPX will be set up on eth0  
and the network frame type is 802.2.  You should confirm that these 
are the correct settings and adjust as necessary.</para>

<para><screen>cat &gt; /etc/sysconfig/network-devices/ifup-ipx0 &lt;&lt; "EOF"
#!/bin/sh
# Begin /etc/sysconfig/network-devices/ifup-ipx0

source /etc/sysconfig/rc || exit
source $rc_functions || exit

echo "Setting up the IPX protocol on eth0..."
/sbin/ipx_interface add eth0 802.2 &&
/sbin/ipx_configure --auto_interface=on --auto_primary=on
evaluate_retval

# End /etc/sysconfig/network-devices/ifup-ipx0
EOF
cat &gt; /etc/sysconfig/network-devices/ifdown-ipx0 &lt;&lt; "EOF"
#!/bin/sh
# Begin /etc/sysconfig/network-devices/ifdown-ipx0

source /etc/sysconfig/rc || exit
source $rc_functions || exit

echo "Stoping IPX on the eth0 interface..."
/usr/bin/ipx_configure --auto_interface=off --auto_primary=off &&
/usr/bin/ipx_interface del eth0 802.2
evaluate_retval

# End /etc/sysconfig/network-devices/ifdown-ipx0
EOF
echo "ONBOOT=yes" &gt; /etc/sysconfig/network-devices/ifconfig.ipx0
chmod 755 /etc/sysconfig/network-devices/ifup-ipx0
chmod 755 /etc/sysconfig/network-devices/ifdown-ipx0</screen></para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

