<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<!-- $LastChangedBy: randy $
   $Date: 2009-01-14 12:27:42 $ -->

<preface id="preface" xreflabel="Preface">
  <?dbhtml filename="preface.html" dir="preface"?>

  <title>Préface</title>

<para>Après m'être occupé de Linux From Scratch pendant un moment, j'ai remarqué que nous recevions de nombreuses demandes sur la manière de continuer au delà du système de base LFS. A ce moment, la seule aide existante à propos de LFS était les astuces LFS (<ulink url="&hints-root;"/>). La plupart des astuces sont très bien écrites, mais je (et d'autres) pouvais quand même voir un besoin d'aide plus compréhensive pour aller au delà de LFS.
</para>

<para>Le but de BLFS est d'être plus que les astuces LFS converties en XML, bien que la majorité de notre travail est basé sur les astuces et que certaines personnes ont rédigés les astuces aussi bien que des parties des BLFS. Nous esperons que nous pourrons vous donner assez d'informations, non seulement pour être capable de construire le système que vous désirez, que ce soit un serveur web ou un ordinateur de bureau, mais aussi pour que vous puissiez apprendre beaucoup à propos de la configuration d'un système.</para>


<para>Remerciements à tout les membres de la communauté LFS/BLFS; en particulier à ceux qui ont contribué aux instructions, écrit le texte, répondu aux question et crié lorsque quelque chose n'allait pas!</para>


<para>Pour terminer, nous vous encourageons à rejoindre la communauté; posez des questions sur la mailing list ??or news gateways?? et rejoiniez le fun sur #lfs sur irc.&lfs-domainname;. Vous pouvez trouver plus de détails à propos de tout cela dans la section <xref linkend="introduction"/> du livre.</para>


<para>Appreciez BLFS!</para>

  <blockquote>
<literallayout>Mark Hymers
markh &lt;at&gt; &lfs-domainname;
BLFS Editor (July 2001&ndash;March 2003)</literallayout>
  </blockquote>

  <para>I still remember how I found the BLFS project
  and started using the instructions that were completed at the time.  I could
  not believe how wonderful it was to get an application up and running very
  quickly, with explanations as to why things were done a certain way.
  Unfortunately, for me, it wasn't long before I was opening applications that
  had nothing more  than "To be done" on the page.  I did what most would do,
  I waited for someone else to do it.  It wasn't too long before I am looking
  through  <application>Bugzilla</application> for something easy to do.
  As with any learning experience, the definition of what was easy kept
  changing.</para>

  <para>We still encourage you to become involved as BLFS is
  never really finished.  Contributing or just using, we hope you enjoy
  your BLFS experience.</para>

  <blockquote>
<literallayout>Larry Lawrence
larry &lt;at&gt; &lfs-domainname;
BLFS Editor (March 2003&ndash;June 2004)</literallayout>
  </blockquote>

  <para>The BLFS project is a natural progression of
  LFS.  Together, these projects provide a unique resource for
  the Open Source Community.  They take the mystery out of the process of
  building a complete, functional software system from the source code contributed
  by many talented individuals throughout the world.  They truly allow users
  to implement the slogan "Your distro, your rules."</para>

  <para>Our goal is to continue to provide the best resource available that shows
  you how to integrate many significant Open Source applications.  Since these
  applications are constantly updated and new applications are developed, this
  book will never be complete.  Additionally, there is always room for
  improvement in explaining the nuances of how to install the different packages.
  To make these improvements, we need your feedback.  I encourage you to
  participate on the different mailing lists, news groups, and
  IRC channels to help meet these goals.</para>

  <blockquote>
<literallayout>Bruce Dubbs
bdubbs &lt;at&gt; &lfs-domainname;
BLFS Editor (June 2004&ndash;December 2006)</literallayout>
  </blockquote>

  <para>My introduction to the [B]LFS project was actually by accident. I
  was trying to build a <application>GNOME</application> environment using
  some how-tos and other information I found on the web. A couple of times
  I ran into some build issues and Googling pulled up some old BLFS mailing
  list messages. Out for curiosity, I visited the Linux From Scratch web site
  and shortly thereafter was hooked. I've not used any other Linux
  distribution for personal use since.</para>

  <para>I can't promise anyone will feel the sense of satisfaction I felt
  after building my first few systems using [B]LFS instructions, but I
  sincerely hope that your BLFS experience is as rewarding for you as it has
  been for me.</para>

  <para>The BLFS project has grown significantly the last couple of years.
  There are more package instructions and related dependencies than ever
  before. The project requires your input for continued success. If you
  discover that you enjoy building BLFS, please consider helping out in any
  way you can. BLFS requires hundreds of hours of maintenance to keep it
  even semi-current. If you feel confident enough in your editing skills,
  please consider joining the BLFS team. Simply contributing to the mailing
  list discussions with sound advice and/or providing patches to the book's
  XML will probably result in you receiving an invitation to join the
  team.</para>

  <blockquote>
<literallayout>Randy McMurchy
randy &lt;at&gt; &lfs-domainname;
BLFS Editor (December 2006&ndash;Present)</literallayout>
  </blockquote>

  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="foreword.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="whoread.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="organization.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="errata.xml"/>

</preface>
