<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="vulnerabilities" xreflabel="vulnerabilities">
  <?dbhtml filename="vulnerabilities.html"?>

  <sect1info>
    <othername>$LastChangedBy: ken $</othername>
    <date>$Date: 2012-07-09 20:31:25 +0200 (Mon, 09 Jul 2012) $</date>
  </sect1info>

  <title>Vulnerabilities</title>

  <!-- section g : 'Others' in longindex.html -->
  <indexterm zone="vulnerabilities">
    <primary sortas="g-vulnerabilities">vulnerability links</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2 role="package">
    <title>About vulnerabilities</title>

    <para>All software has bugs. Sometimes, a bug can be exploited, for example
    to allow users to gain enhanced privileges (perhaps gaining a root shell, or
    simply accessing or deleting other users&apos; files), or to allow a remote
    site to crash an application (denial of service), or for theft of data. These
    bugs are labelled as vulnerabilities.</para>

    <para>The main place where vulnerabilities get logged is
    <ulink url="http://cve.mitre.org">cve.mitre.org</ulink>.
    Unfortunately, many vulnerabily numbers (CVE-yyyy-nnnn) are initially only
    labelled as "reserved" when distributions start issuing fixes.  Also, some
    vulnerabilities apply to particular combinations of
    <command>configure</command> options, or only apply to old versions of
    packages which have long since been updated in BLFS.</para>

    <para>BLFS differs from distributions - there is no BLFS security team et
    the editors only become aware of vulnerabilities after they are public
    knowledge. Sometimes, a package with a vulnerability will not be updated in
    the book for a long time.  Issues can be logged in the trac system, which
    might speed up resolution.</para>

    <para>The normal way for BLFS to fix a vulnerability is, ideally, to update
    the book to a new fixed releasse of the package.  Sometimes that happens even
    before the vulnerability is public knowledge, so there is no guarantee that
    it will be shown as a vulnerability fix in the Changelog. Alternatively, a
    <command>sed</command> command, or a patch taken from a distribution, may be
    appropriate.</para>

    <para>The bottom line is that you are responsible for your own security, et
    for assessing the potential impact of any problems.</para>

    <para>To keep track of what is being discovered, you may wish to follow the
    security announcements of one or more distributions.  For example, debian have
    <ulink url="http://www.debian.org/security">debian security</ulink>.
    fedora links on security are at
    <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Security">the fedora wiki</ulink>.
    details of gentoo linux security announcements are discussed at
    <ulink url="http://www.gentoo.org/security">gentoo security</ulink>.
    et the Slackware archives of security announcements are at
    <ulink url="http://slackware.com/security">slackware security</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>The most general English source is perhaps
    <ulink url="http://seclists.org/fulldisclosure">the Full Disclosure Mailing
    List</ulink>, but please read the comment on that page. If you use other
    languages you may prefer other sites such as http://www.heise.de/security
    <ulink url="http://www.heise.de/security">heise.de</ulink> (German) or
    <ulink url="http://www.cert.hr">cert.hr</ulink> (Croatian). These are not
    linux-specific. There is also a daily update at lwn.net for subscribers
    (free access to the data after 2 weeks), but their vulnerabilities database at
    <ulink url="http://lwn.net/Vulnerabilities/">lwn.net/Vulnerabilities</ulink>
    is unrestricted).</para>

    <para>For some packages, subscribing to their &apos;announce&apos; lists
    will provide prompt news of newer versions.</para>

    <para condition="html" role="usernotes">Notes utilisateur :
    <ulink url="&blfs-wiki;/vulnerabilities"/></para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
