<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="la-files" xreflabel="Fichiers d'archive libtool (.la)">
  <?dbhtml filename="la-files.html"?>

  <sect1info>
<date>$Date$</date></sect1info>

  <title>À propos des fichiers d'archive libtool (.la)</title>

  
  <indexterm zone="la-files">
    <!-- section g : 'Others' in longindex.html -->
<primary sortas="g-la-files">Fichiers d'archives de bibliothèques (.la)</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2 role="package">
    <title>Fichiers avec une extension .la</title>

    <para>

      In LFS and BLFS, many packages use a internally shipped libtool copy to
build on a variety of Unix platforms.  This includes platforms such as AIX,
Solaris, IRIX, HP-UX, and Cygwin as well as Linux.  The origins of this tool
are quite dated.  It was intended to manage libraries on systems with less
advanced capabilities than a modern Linux system.

    </para>

    <para>

      On a Linux system, libtool specific files are generally unneeded.  Normally
libraries are specified in the build process during the link phase.  Since a
linux system uses the <ulink
url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Executable_and_Linkable_Format">
Executable and Linkable Format (ELF)</ulink> for executables and dynamic
libraries, information needed to complete the task is embedded in the
files.  Both the linker and the program loader can query the appropriate
files and properly link or execute the program.

    </para>

    <para>
      Static libraries are rarely used in LFS and BLFS.  And, nowadays most
packages store the information needed for linking against a static library
into a .pc file, instead of relying on libtool.  A <command>pkg-config
--static --libs</command> command will output the sufficient flags for the
linker to link against a static library without any libtool magic.
    </para>

    <para>
      The problem is that libtool usually creates one or more text files for
package libraries called libtool archives.  These small files have a ".la"
extension and contain information that is similar to that embedded in the
libraries or pkg-config files.  When building a package that uses libtool,
the process automatically looks for these files.  Sometimes a .la file can
contains the name or path of a static library used during build but not
installed, then the build process will break because the .la file refers to
something nonexistent on the system.  Similarly, if a package is updated and
no longer uses the .la file, then the build process can break with the old
.la files.
    </para>

    <para>

       La solution consiste à supprimer les fichiers .la, mais il y a un
inconvénient. Certains paquets, comme <xref linkend='imagemagick'/>,
utilisent une fonction de libtool, lt_dlopen, pour charger les bibliothèques
requises pendant l'exécution et résoudre leurs dépendances à
l'exécution. Dans ce cas, les fichiers .la ne doivent pas être supprimés.

    </para>

    <para>

        Le script ci-dessous supprime tous les fichiers .la inutiles et les
sauvegarde dans un répertoire, /var/local/la-files par défaut, qui ne se
trouve pas dans le chemin de recherche habituel des bibliothèques. Il
recherche également les références à des fichiers .la dans les fichiers
pkg-config (.pc) et les transforme en références de bibliothèques
conventionnelles qui sont nécessaires lors de la construction d'une
application ou d'une bibliothèque. Il peut être lancé au besoin pour
nettoyer les répertoires qui causent des problèmes.

    </para>

<screen role="root"><userinput>cat &gt; /usr/sbin/remove-la-files.sh &lt;&lt; "EOF"
<literal>#!/bin/bash

# /usr/sbin/remove-la-files.sh
# Written for Beyond Linux From Scratch
# by Bruce Dubbs &lt;bdubbs@&lfs-domainname;&gt;

# Make sure we are running with root privs
if test "${EUID}" -ne 0; then
    echo "Error: $(basename ${0}) must be run as the root user! Exiting..."
    exit 1
fi

# Make sure PKG_CONFIG_PATH is set if discarded by sudo
source /etc/profile

OLD_LA_DIR=/var/local/la-files

mkdir -p $OLD_LA_DIR

# Only search directories in /opt, but not symlinks to directories
OPTDIRS=$(find /opt -mindepth 1 -maxdepth 1 -type d)

# Move any found .la files to a directory out of the way
find /usr/lib $OPTDIRS -name "*.la" ! -path "/usr/lib/ImageMagick*" \
  -exec mv -fv {} $OLD_LA_DIR \;
###############

# Fix any .pc files that may have .la references

STD_PC_PATH='/usr/lib/pkgconfig
             /usr/share/pkgconfig
             /usr/local/lib/pkgconfig
             /usr/local/share/pkgconfig'

# For each directory that can have .pc files
for d in $(echo $PKG_CONFIG_PATH | tr : ' ') $STD_PC_PATH; do

  # For each pc file
  for pc in $d/*.pc ; do
    if [ $pc == "$d/*.pc" ]; then continue; fi

    # Check each word in a line with a .la reference
    for word in $(grep '\.la' $pc); do
      if $(echo $word | grep -q '.la$' ); then
        mkdir -p $d/la-backup
        cp -fv  $pc $d/la-backup

        basename=$(basename $word )
        libref=$(echo $basename|sed -e 's/^lib/-l/' -e 's/\.la$//')

        # Fix the .pc file
        sed -i "s:$word:$libref:" $pc
      fi
    done
  done
done</literal>

EOF

chmod +x /usr/sbin/remove-la-files.sh</userinput></screen>

    <para condition="html" role="usernotes">
       Notes utilisateur&nbsp;: <ulink url="&blfs-wiki;/la-files"/>
    </para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
