<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="ch-tools-creatingminlayout">
  <?dbhtml filename="creatingminlayout.html"?>

  <title>Creating a Limited Directory Layout in the LFS Filesystem</title>

  <para>In this section, we begin populating the LFS filesystem with the
  pieces that will constitute the final Linux system. The first step is to
  create a limited directory hierarchy, so that the programs compiled in <xref
  linkend="chapter-temporary-tools"/> (as well as glibc and libstdc++ in <xref
  linkend="chapter-cross-tools"/>) can be installed in their final
  location. We do this so those temporary programs will be overwritten when
  the final versions are built in <xref linkend="chapter-building-system"/>.</para>

  <para>Create the required directory layout by issuing the following commands as
  <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>:</para>

<screen><userinput>mkdir -pv $LFS/{etc,var} $LFS/usr/{bin,lib,sbin}

for i in bin lib sbin; do
  ln -sv usr/$i $LFS/$i
done

case $(uname -m) in
  x86_64) mkdir -pv $LFS/lib64 ;;
esac</userinput></screen>

  <para>Programs in <xref linkend="chapter-temporary-tools"/> will be compiled
  with a cross-compiler (more details can be found in section <xref
  linkend="ch-tools-toolchaintechnotes"/>). This cross-compiler will be installed
  in a special directory, to separate it from the other programs. Still acting as
  &root;, create that directory with this command:</para>

<screen><userinput>mkdir -pv $LFS/tools</userinput></screen>

  <note>
    <para>
      The LFS editors have deliberately decided not to use a
      <filename class="directory">/usr/lib64</filename> directory.  Several
      steps are taken to be sure the toolchain will not use it. If for any
      reason this directory appears (either because you made an error in
      following the instructions, or because you installed a binary package that
      created it after finishing LFS), it may break your system.
      You should always be sure this directory does not exist.
    </para>
  </note>

</sect1>
