<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE bookinfo PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<bookinfo>
  <title>Linux From Scratch</title>
  <subtitle>Version &version;</subtitle>


  <authorgroup>
    <author>
      <firstname>Gerard</firstname>
      <surname>Beekmans</surname>
    </author>
  </authorgroup>


  <copyright id="copyright">
    <year>1999&ndash;2007</year>
    <holder>Gerard Beekmans</holder>
  </copyright>

  <legalnotice>
    <para>Copyright (c) 1999&ndash;2007, Gerard Beekmans</para>

    <para>Tous droits réservés.</para>

    <para>La redistribution et l'utilisation de ces sources et des binaires,
    avec ou sans modifications, sont autorisées dans les conditions suivantes&nbsp;:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Les redistributions sous quelque forme que ce soit doivent mentionner
        le copyright ci-dessus,  la présente liste de conditions et les
        avertissements ci-dessous</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Ni le nom of <quote>Linux From Scratch</quote> ni le nom de ses
        contributeurs ne peut être utilisé pour  la garantie ou la promotion
        de produits tirés de ce contenu sans consentement préalable écrit</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Tout dérivé  de Linux From Scratch deit contenir une réfïrence au
        projet <quote>Linux From Scratch</quote>..</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND
    CONTRIBUTORS <quote>AS IS</quote> AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED
    WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
    MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED.
    IN NO EVENT SHALL THE REGENTS OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL
    DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE
    GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS
    INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER
    IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR
    OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN
    IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</para>

  </legalnotice>

</bookinfo>
