<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE partintro PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>
<partintro>
  <title>Introduction à GNOME</title>
  
  
  <para>This chapter presents the instructions to install a complete
  GNOME-&gnome-version;&gnome-minor-version; desktop environment. The order of
  the installed packages follows the build order defined by the GNOME
  development team et has been thoroughly tested by the BLFS team.</para>
  <para>The installation of GNOME-&gnome-version;&gnome-minor-version; is a
  large undertaking et one we would like to see you complete with the least
  amount of stress. One of the first goals in this installation is to protect
  your previously installed software, especially if you are testing GNOME on
  your machine. GNOME-&gnome-version; packages utilize the
  <option>--prefix=option</option> passed to <command>configure</command>,
  so you will use that et an environment variable (<envar>GNOME_PREFIX</envar>)
  to add flexibility to the installation.</para>
  <para>To install GNOME as your desktop of choice, it is recommended that you
  install using <option>--prefix=/usr</option>. If you are not sure that you
  are going to keep the GNOME installation, or you think you will update to the
  newest releases as they become available, you should install with
  <option>--prefix=/opt/gnome-&gnome-version;&gnome-minor-version;</option>.
  Setting the environment variable et the additional edits required by the
  second option are covered in the Pre-Installation Configuration
  section.</para>
  <para>If you choose the second option, removal of
  GNOME-&gnome-version;&gnome-minor-version; is as easy as removing the edits
  from the pre-installation page et issuing the following command (you may
  need to become the <systemitem class='username'>root</systemitem>
  user):</para>
<screen role="root">
<userinput>rm -rf /opt/gnome-&gnome-version;&gnome-minor-version;</userinput>
</screen>
  <para>If your system was completely built per LFS et BLFS instructions,
  you have a very good chance of using
  GNOME-&gnome-version;&gnome-minor-version; after your first installation. If
  you are a typical LFS user, you have made modifications to the instructions
  along the way knowing that you have to take those modifications into account
  on future installations. You should have no problems integrating
  GNOME-&gnome-version;&gnome-minor-version; into your unique setup, but you
  will have to install well over 50 packages before you can run GNOME through
  any testing (assuming your windowing system is preinstalled et tested). You
  should anticipate that you will be rebuilding GNOME at least once to make
  adjustments for your setup.</para>
  
  <bridgehead renderas="sect3">Alternate Installation Methods</bridgehead>
  <para>As was previously mentioned, building a GNOME desktop from sources is a
  significant project. Some may find it too tedious or time-consuming to perform
  a full installation following the BLFS book. You may wish to review the
  automated methods mentioned in the GNOME-&gnome-version; <ulink
  url="http://www.gnome.org/start/&gnome-version;/notes/en/rninstallation.html">Release
  Notes</ulink>. Note that using any other method to install
  GNOME-&gnome-version;&gnome-minor-version; other than using the BLFS
  instructions cannot be supported by the BLFS team. Alternate methods are only
  mentioned as a courtesy to builders who would like to build GNOME from sources
  but do not have the time/desire/patience/whatever to follow the BLFS
  book.</para>
</partintro>
