<partintro>
<title>Introduction to <acronym>KDE</acronym></title>

<para><acronym>KDE</acronym> is a comprehensive desktop environment that
builds on an <application>X</application> Window System and
<application>Qt</application> to provide
a window manager and many user tools, including a browser, word processor, 
spreadsheet, presentation package, games, and numerous other utilities. It 
provides extensive capabilities for customization.</para>

<para>The <acronym>KDE</acronym> instructions are divided into two parts. The first part, the
core packages, are needed for the rest of <acronym>KDE</acronym> to work. The second part
presents additional packages which provide functionality in various areas
(multimedia, graphics, etc.).</para> 

<para>There are two alternatives for installing <acronym>KDE</acronym>. Option one, that
is used by most of the commercial distributions, is to
install <acronym>KDE</acronym> in the standard system prefix: <filename>/usr</filename>.
This option allows the use of KDE without the need for any additional configuration such
as modification of various environment variables or configuration files. Option two is
to install it in a unique prefix such as <filename>/opt/kde</filename> or
<filename>/opt/kde-&kde-version;</filename>. This option allows for easy removal of
the package.</para>

<tip>
<para>All the <acronym>KDE</acronym> packages are comprised of various components. 
The default is to
install most of the components. If specific components are to be eliminated, the
official way is to set the variable <envar>DO_NOT_COMPILE</envar>.
This comes in handy when there are problems compiling a particular
component.</para>

<screen><userinput><command>DO_NOT_COMPILE="component1 component2" \
    ./configure --prefix=&kde-dir; ...</command></userinput></screen>

<para>The core <acronym>KDE</acronym> packages also honor this variable, but omitting components
from the core packages is not advisable since it may result in an
incomplete <acronym>KDE</acronym> installation.</para>
</tip>

<note><para>In each of the packages,
one other option to <command>configure</command> can be added: 
<parameter>--enable-final</parameter>. This option can speed up the build 
process, but requires a lot of memory. If you have less than 256MB of RAM, 
this option may cause swapping and significantly slow compilation.</para></note>

</partintro>
