<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="ch-intro-how">
  <?dbhtml filename="how.html"?>

  <title>How to Build an LFS System</title>

  <para>The LFS system will be built by using an already installed
  Linux distribution (such as Debian, OpenMandriva, Fedora, or openSUSE). This
  existing Linux system (the host) will be used as a starting point to
  provide necessary programs, including a compiler, linker, and shell,
  to build the new system. Select the <quote>development</quote> option
  during the distribution installation to include these
  tools.</para>

  <para>As an alternative to installing a separate distribution on your
  machine, you may wish to use <!-- the Linux From Scratch LiveCD or --> a LiveCD from a
  commercial distribution. <!-- The LFS LiveCD works well as a host system,
  providing all the tools you need to successfully follow the instructions in
  this book. The LiveCD version is behind the current book, but is still useful
  as a host for building the current book.  The <quote>-nosrc</quote> or
  <quote>-min</quote> editions of the LiveCD are the most appropriate for
  building a current LFS system.  For more information about the LFS LiveCD or
  to download a copy, visit <ulink url="&livecd-root;"/>. --></para>

  <!--
  <note>
    <para>The LFS LiveCD might not work on newer hardware configurations,
    failing to boot or failing to detect some devices such as some SATA hard
    drives.</para>
  </note> -->

  <para><xref linkend="chapter-partitioning"/> of this book describes how
  to create a new Linux native partition and file system,
  where the new LFS system will be compiled and installed. <xref
  linkend="chapter-getting-materials"/> explains which packages and
  patches must be downloaded to build an LFS system, and how to store
  them on the new file system. <xref linkend="chapter-final-preps"/>
  discusses the setup of an appropriate working environment. Please read
  <xref linkend="chapter-final-preps"/> carefully as it explains several
  important issues you should be aware of before you begin to
  work your way through <xref linkend="chapter-cross-tools"/> and beyond.</para>

  <para><xref linkend="chapter-cross-tools"/>  explains the installation of
  the initial tool chain, (binutils, gcc, and glibc) using cross-compilation
  techniques to isolate the new tools from the host system.</para>

  <para><xref linkend="chapter-temporary-tools"/> shows you how to
  cross-compile basic utilities using the just built cross-toolchain.</para>

  <para><xref linkend="chapter-chroot-temporary-tools"/> then enters a
  "chroot" environment, which uses the new tools to build all
  the rest of the tools needed to create the LFS system.</para>

  <para>This effort to isolate the new system from the host distribution may
  seem excessive. A full technical explanation as to why this is done is
  provided in <xref linkend="ch-tools-toolchaintechnotes"/>.</para>

  <para>In <xref linkend="chapter-building-system"/> the
  full-blown LFS system is built. Another advantage provided by the chroot
  environment is that it allows you to continue using the host system
  while LFS is being built. While waiting for package compilations to
  complete, you can continue using your computer as usual.</para>

  <para>To finish the installation, the basic system configuration is set up in
  <xref linkend="chapter-config"/>, and the kernel and boot loader are created
  in <xref linkend="chapter-bootable"/>. <xref linkend="chapter-finalizing"/>
  contains information on continuing the LFS experience beyond this book.
  After the steps in this chapter have been implemented, the computer is
  ready to boot into the new LFS system.</para>

  <para>This is the process in a nutshell. Detailed information on each
  step is presented in the following chapters.
  Items that seem complicated now will be clarified, and everything will
  fall into place as you commence your LFS adventure.</para>

</sect1>
