<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="whichsections" xreflabel="Quelles sections du livre&nbsp;?">
  <?dbhtml filename="which.html"?>

  <sect1info>
<date>$Date$</date></sect1info>

  <title>Quelles sections du livre m'intéressent&nbsp;?</title>

  <para>Unlike the Linux From Scratch book, BLFS isn't designed to be followed in a
linear manner. LFS provides instructions on how to create a base system
which can become anything from a web server to a multimedia desktop
system. BLFS attempts to guide you in the process of going from the base
system to your intended destination. Choice is very much involved.</para>

  <para>Everyone who reads this book will want to read certain sections.  The <xref
linkend="introduction"/>, which you are currently reading, contains generic
information.  Take special note of the information in <xref
linkend="important"/>, as this contains comments about how to unpack
software, issues related to the use of different locales, and various other
considerations which apply throughout the book.</para>

  <para>The part on <xref linkend="postlfs"/> is where most people will want to turn
next.  This deals not only with configuration, but also with Security (<xref
linkend="postlfs-security"/>), File Systems (<xref
linkend="postlfs-filesystems"/> -- including GRUB for UEFI), Editors (<xref
linkend="postlfs-editors"/>), and Shells (<xref
linkend="postlfs-shells"/>).  Indeed, you may wish to reference some parts
of this chapter (especially the sections on Editors and File Systems) while
building your LFS system.</para>

  <para>Following these basic items, most people will want to at least browse
through the <xref linkend="general"/> part of the book.  This contains
information on many items which are prerequisites for other sections of the
book, as well as some items (such as <xref linkend="general-prog"/>)  which
are useful in their own right.  You don't have to install all of the
libraries and packages found in this part; each BLFS installation procedure
tells you which other packages this one depends upon. You can choose the
program you want to install, and see what it needs. (Don't forget to check
for nested dependencies!)</para>

  <para>Likewise, most people will probably want to look at the <xref
linkend="basicnet"/> section.  It deals with connecting to the Internet or
your LAN (<xref linkend="basicnet-connect"/>)  using a variety of methods
such as DHCP and PPP, and with items such as Networking Libraries (<xref
linkend="basicnet-netlibs"/>), plus various basic networking programs and
utilities.</para>

  <para>Once you have dealt with these basics, you may wish to configure more
advanced network services.  These are dealt with in the <xref
linkend="server"/> part of the book.  Those wanting to build servers should
find a good starting point there.  Note that this section also contains
information on several database packages.</para>

  <para>The next twelve chapters deal with desktop systems.  This portion of the
book starts with a part talking about <xref linkend="x"/>. This part also
deals with some generic X-based libraries (<xref linkend="x-lib"/>).  After
that, <xref linkend="kde"/>, <xref linkend="gnome"/>, <xref
linkend="xfce"/>, and <xref linkend="lxde"/> are given their own parts,
followed by one on <xref linkend="xsoft"/>.</para>

  <para>The book then moves on to deal with <xref linkend="multimedia"/>
packages. Note that many people may want to use the <xref linkend="alsa"/>
instructions from this chapter when first starting their BLFS journey; the
instructions are placed here because it is the most logical place for them.</para>

  <para>The final part of the main BLFS book deals with <xref linkend="pst"/>.  This
is useful for most people with desktop systems, but even those who are
creating dedicated server systems may find it useful.</para>

  <para>We hope you enjoy using BLFS. May you realize your dream of building the
perfectly personalized Linux system!</para>

</sect1>
