<sect2>
<title>Contents</title>

<para>The ucspi-tcp package contains <userinput>tcpserver, tcprules, 
tcprulescheck, argv0, fixcrio, recordio, rblsmtpd, tcpclient, who@,
date@, finger@, http@, tcpcat, mconnect, addcr, delcr</userinput></para>

<para>You can also find detailed descriptions of each of these programs at 
http://cr.yp.to/ucspi-tcp/tcpserver.html, but here is a brief summary:</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title>Description</title>

<sect3><title>tcpserver</title>
<para>tcpserver listens for incoming tcp connections on a given port, and runs 
a program of your choosing in response to a connection.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>tcprules</title>
<para>tcprules compiles rules that govern access control for tcpserver into a 
fast access database format.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>tcprulescheck</title>
<para>tcprulescheck makes it possible to see how tcpserver will react to 
connections from a given address without actually having to connect via that 
address. This is useful for checking to see if the access control rules you 
are using are doing what you expected.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>argv0</title>
<para>argv0 runs a given program with a specified 0th argument.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>fixcrio</title>
<para>fixcrio inserts carriage returns at the end of lines when they are 
missing.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>recordio</title>
<para>recordio records all input and output of a program given as an 
argument.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>rblsmtpd</title>
<para>rblsmtpd is a spam blocking program that works in conjunction with your 
smtp daemon and tcpserver.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>tcpclient</title>
<para>tcpclient creates a connection to a tcp port for a given 
program.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>who@</title>
<para>who@ is a demonstration program using tcpclient that has the 
functionality of the rwho program. It requires a server running sysstat 
on port 11.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>date@</title>
<para>date@ is a demonstration program using tcpclient that will return the 
system time of a remote host which is running a daytime service on 
port 13.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>finger@</title>
<para>finger@ is a demonstration program using tcpclient that mimics the 
functionality of the finger program. It requires a server running fingerd 
on port 79.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>http@</title>
<para>http@ downloads web pages from web servers.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>tcpcat</title>
<para>tcpcat connects to a tcp port and prints all that is returned from the 
port.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>mconnect</title>
<para>mconnect connects to a tcp port, delivers any input specified to the 
port, and prints any output from the port.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>addcr</title>
<para>addcr adds carriage returns to files. This and delcr are useful for 
converting between Windows to UNIX file formats.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>delcr</title>
<para>delcr removes carriage returns from files.</para></sect3>

</sect2>

