<sect1 id="ch06-introduction"><title>Introduction</title><?dbhtml filename="introduction.html" dir="chapter06"?> <para>The installation of all the software is pretty straightforward, andyou will probably think it would be so much easier and shorter to givethe generic installation instructions for a package here and only explainin full the installation of those packages that require an alternatemethod. Although we agree with that, we choose to give the full instructions for each and every package, simply to avoid any possible confusion and errors.</para><para>L'installation de tous les logiciels est plutôt simple etvous allez probablement penser qu'il est tellement plus facile etplus court de donner les instructions génériques d'installation pourun package et de seulement expliquer en détail l'installation des packagesnécessitant une méthode alternative. Même si nous sommes d'accord avec ceci,nous avons choisi de donner les instructions complètes pour chaque package.Il s'agit simplement d'éviter toute confusion ou erreur.</para><para>Now would be a good time to take a look at the optimization hint at <ulink url="&hints-root;optimization.txt"/> if you plan to use compiler optimization for the packagesinstalled in this chapter. Compiler optimization can make a program runfaster, but may also cause compilation problems. If you run into problemswhen using optimization, always try it without optimization to see if the problem persists.</para><para>Ce serait le bon moment pour jeter un oeil aux astuces d'optimisationdans <ulink url="&hints-root;optimization.txt" />si vous prévoyez d'utiliser des options d'optimisations lors la compilationdes packages du chapitre qui suit. Les options d'optimisation peuvent fairequ'un programme s'exécute plus vite, mais peuvent également causer des problèmesde compilation. Si vous rencontrez des problèmes après avoir utilisé lesoptimisations, essayez toujours sans optimisations pour voir si le problèmepersiste.</para><para>Please refrain from installing more than one package at a time, evenif it may save you time (especially with dual CPU machines). If you installthe wrong package at the wrong time, it may hard-wire program paths to<filename class="directory">$LFS/static</filename> which will cause theprograms to stop working once the static directory is removed. The orderpackages are installed in this chapter have to be followed exactly to besure nothing is hard-wiring the static paths.</para></sect1>